<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<GrannysTips>
  <Item>
    <title>Dandruff</title>
    <ImagePath>images/GrannyTips/Remedies_for_Dandruff.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Dandruff</Element>
    <Description>
      Granny Says:- Do not worry
      Follow the simple steps described in this section.I am sure your problem would be solved. 
      
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.
    </Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>Follow the simple steps given below.I am sure your problem would be solved.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Massage the Scalp with pure coconut oil. This will also help growth of hair.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Apply coconut oil which has been boiled with small onions for about 20 minutes. Wash it off with a mixture of green gram powder and water drained from cooked (boiled) rice.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Apply a mixture of almond oil and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gooseberry">gooseberry&lt;/a> juice with finger tips on the scalp.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Apply the warm mixture of olive oil, lemon juice and coconut oil. Do a steam towel- wrap for 15 minutes and wash the hair with a mild shampoo.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Apply a paste of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fenugreek">fenugreek&lt;/a> and mustard to the scalp.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mix &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shikakai">Shikakai&lt;/a> powder with the water drained from cooked rice and wash the hair with it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Crush the leaves of five petal hibiscus flower and take the juice. Wash the hair with this juice.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Heat oil with a little camphor. Apply the oil in the scalp and massage for 10 minutes. After 30 minutes wash the hair with an herbal shampoo. Do the steam towel- wrap for 15 minutes.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>
</Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Healthy and Shiny Hair</title>
    <ImagePath>images/GrannyTips/Tips_for_Healthy_and_Shiny_hair.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>HealthyShinyHair</Element>
    <Description>Granny recommended tips are described in this section.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>Granny recommends following tips - &lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>It is better to apply castor oil for a healthy growth of hair.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Wash hair with tea once in a week.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Apply &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Besan">besan&lt;/a> in the hair and wash it with water drained from the cooked rice.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Soak a handful of gooseberries in a cup of milk for two hours. Make a paste and apply on the hair.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Apply the mixture of an egg white, 2 spoons of castor oil, 1 spoon glycerin, in the scalp and hair. Wash it after some time.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Massage hair with warm coconut oil an hour before washing. Let it soak. Cover your head with a hot towel and wash your hair after an hour or so.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Boil a few hibiscus flowers in coconut oil. Filter and use this hair oil to control hair loss and thinning.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Do a 'steam-towel-wrap' once in a while, if your cuticles are damaged, as this steaming opens out the pores and absorbs the oil.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Soak 1 teaspoon &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fenugreek">fenugreek&lt;/a> in curd and keep it for a night. Apply it in the next morning.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Boil coconut oil with the juices of curry leaves, basil, hibiscus flower and gooseberry. Apply on hair, keep it for sometime and rinse.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Daily application of coconut oil mixed with lime- juice on the hair is also beneficial. Applying juice of green coriander leaves on the head is also good.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Washing the hair with a paste of cooked Urad dal (black beans) and fenugreek (methi) 2-3 times a week.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Take some coconut and mustard oil. Soak half a cup of curry leaves in the oil mixture and keep it for a night. Next morning, heat on a slow flame till the curry leaves turn crisp. Remove from heat and add two to three camphor balls. Allow oil to cool and then strain. Apply oil to hair roots using cotton wool along the parting and massage in circular movements. Leave the oil overnight and shampoo the next morning. Repeat twice a week.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rub the scalp vigorously after washing the hair. It increases the blood circulation, and activates the sebaceous glands.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A mixture of lettuce and spinach juice is good to drink to induce hair growth. The juice of alfalfa mixed with that of carrot, and lettuce juice is also good to take.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Grey Hair</title>
    <ImagePath>images/GrannyTips/Remedies_against_Greying_of_Hair.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>GreyHair</Element>
    <Description>Granny Says:-My hair is still jet black. If you also want hair like me then follow my tips described in this section.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode. </Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>Granny Says - My hair is still jet black. If you also want hair like me then follow my tips described below.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Take a little &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henna">Henna&lt;/a>, an egg, juice of  half a lemon, one table spoon of instant coffee powder. Mix it together and apply on the hair. Wash it after 45 minutes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Boil one cup of dried gooseberry with 4 cups of water. Add a pinch of sugar in it. Keep boiling till the quantity of the liquid reduces to one cup. Mix 2 cups of Henna, an egg, juice of a lemon and the gooseberry solution and apply on hair. Wash the hair after two hours.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Natural Conditioners</title>
    <ImagePath>images/GrannyTips/Natural_Conditioners.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>NaturalConditioners</Element>
    <Description>Granny Says:- For healthy hair follow my tips given below.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;ul>&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henna">Henna&lt;/a> is a herbal treatment with good conditioning abilities.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Egg white is a good conditioner for hair.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Deep condition with curd, beer and egg.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mix a little vinegar in warm water and rinse your hair with this solution. This will add bounce to dull and lifeless hair.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>&lt;/p>
    </Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Hair Loss</title>
    <ImagePath>images/GrannyTips/Remedies_against_Hair_Loss.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>HairLoss</Element>
    <Description>Granny Says:-Oh Dont you worry, I had faced it too, but now I know what to do in this situation.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>Granny Says:-Oh Don't you worry, I had faced it too, but now I know what to do in this situation.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>    
&lt;li>Massage the scalp gently with coconut or almond oil daily for 10 to 15 minutes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Boil neem leaves in water. Cool, strain and rinse hair with it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Increase green leafy vegetables, salads, milk, fruits and sprouts in the diet. Take more proteins, milk, buttermilk, yeast, wheat germ, soya beans, whole grains and nuts.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Skin Care</title>
    <ImagePath>images/GrannyTips/Skin_Care.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>SkinCares</Element>
    <Description>Granny Says:-My grandchildren tell me that I look as young as their mother. Here is my secret of looking young.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>Granny Says:-My grandchildren tell me that I look as young as their mother. Here is my secret of looking young.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>In a bowl, mash a ripened banana along with milk and apply it on the face. Leave it for twenty minutes to set and then rinse off with water.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Combine one teaspoon of walnut powder with lemon juice and honey. Mix well to form a thick paste. Scrub the entire body with the paste and let it sit for at least twenty minutes. Finally, wash with cold water.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add a dash of turmeric powder to orange juice. Now, scrub this on the area that is most often exposed to the sun or cold. After twenty minutes, rinse it with cold water.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Prepare a face mask by mixing equal proportions of curd and cucumber juice. You can also mash a ripened papaya and apply it on the face to get radiant skin.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In a bowl mix 1 tablespoon of honey and 1 tablespoon of yogurt. Now apply the mixture on your face and let it sit for about fifteen minutes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In a bowl, mix 4 tbsp Clay, 2 tbsp Lemon pulp, 2 tbsp Honey, 2 tbsp Water, 2 drops Jojoba oil. Apply the mixture on the face and leave it on for fifteen minutes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Make a paste by mixing one tablespoon of mango peels powder and one teaspoon of milk powder. Scrub the gooey mixture on the skin. Do this at least once a week to achieve the desired results.&lt;/li>
    </Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Dark Circles under the Eyes</title>
    <ImagePath>images/GrannyTips/Remedies_for_Dark_Circles_under_the_Eyes.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>DarkCircle</Element>
    <Description>Granny Says:-I know thise nasty circles doesnt look good on you. Don't worry there is a way get rid of them.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>Granny Says:-I know these nasty circles doesn't look good on you. Don't worry there is a way get rid of them.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Potato juice has bleaching agents in it, so you can take potato juice out and apply it on your skin. You can soak cotton balls in the juice and can keep them on your eyes for at least 20 minutes while having rest.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Grated cucumber juice is very useful for dark circles. You can apply it on the eyes the same way you apply potato juice.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Keep 2 cucumber slices on your eyes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Tea water too reduces the puffiness and dark circles of the eyes and rejuvenates the eyes by refreshing them. You can boil tea in water and restrain the leaves. You can refrigerate this water in the freezer to make ice cubes. Keep these ice cubes on the eyes in a cotton cloth for 20 minutes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Take a teaspoonful of milk powder and add honey to it. Put this paste on the skin on the dark circles. It helps in reducing the dark circles.&lt;/li>
    </Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Cracked Heels</title>
    <ImagePath>images/GrannyTips/Remedies_for_Cracked_Heels.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>CrackedHeals</Element>
    <Description>Granny Says:-I know that can hurt but there is a cure for that. Follow simple tips given in this section and see it for yourself. 
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>Granny Says:-I know that can hurt but there is a cure for that. Follow simple tips given below and see it for yourself.&lt;/p>
 
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Soak your feet in warm water with liberal amounts of baby oil. Pat dry and surround them in plastic wrap so that they stay moist.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Try immersing feet in warm water and honey for 15 minutes. Honey works wonders for treating cracked feet.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Make your own foot lotion by combining baby lotion with spearmint and eucalyptus oil. Massage into feet and cover them in thin cotton socks. Sleep in your lotion-rich socks and then rinse carefully in the morning (your feet may be slippery!).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Scrub your feet every morning with a homemade foot scrub made from 4 tablespoons of salt mixed with ½ cup of baby oil, almond oil, or coconut oil.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Douse feet in petroleum jelly and cover them with clean, soft socks. Dab petroleum jelly on the cracks throughout the day.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Soak the feet in lemon juice for about 10 minutes. Follow this therapy on a weekly basis until one finds a change.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A regular application of a mixture of glycerin and rosewater is known to soothe and cure cracked heels.&lt;/li>
    </Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Common Cold</title>
    <ImagePath>images/GrannyTips/Remedy_for_Common_Cold.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>CommonCold</Element>
    <Description>Granny Says:- No more aacchhhooooo.Follow the steps described in this section and get rid off cold. 
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>Granny Says:- No more aacchhhooooo. Follow these steps and get rid of cold.
&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>	
&lt;li>Take  Steam inhalation with Eucalyptus oil drops.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Take Black pepper powder, Ginger juice and Basil juice mixed with Honey  thrice a day.&lt;/li>

&lt;li>Drink Tea with a few Mint leaves or Ginger or Basil leaves.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Saline gargles are helpful to soothe an itchy and sore throat.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Put few drops of Fresh neem leaves juice in the nostrils.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Vitamin C deficiency can often cause Cold problems. So go for rich natural source of vitamin C like Oranges, Gooseberries, Sweet lime, lemon, Grapes, Guava etc.&lt;/li>

&lt;li>Eating a small piece of Onion (pea size) or sucking a piece of Clove (Laung) helps to get instant relief.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Consume a hot glass of turmeric and ginger mixed in milk.&lt;/li>

&lt;li>Drink hot water with Lemon juice and Honey.	&lt;/li></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Abhyanga - Ayurvedic Massage</title>
    <ImagePath>images/GrannyTips/Abhyanga.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Abhyanga</Element>
    <Description>
Granny Says:-
Abhyanga - The Ayurvedic Daily Massage:

For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.
    </Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>'Abhyanga'&lt;/strong> or &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abhyangha">'Abhyangha'&lt;/a> -- the Ayurvedic oil massage -- is an integral part of the daily routine recommended by this healing system for overall health and well-being.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Precautions&lt;/strong> 
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>It should be done on empty stomach.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The best time to have Abhyanga is in early morning. One should take shower / bath at least half an hour after Abhyanga. Always take hot shower/bath after Abhyanga.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Always use warm/ hot oil for Abhyanga.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;strong>Steps to be followed&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>On limbs (arms and legs), the movement should be towards heart.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Clockwise circular movement over abdomen. Over back it should be in same direction of musculature. i.e. starting from shoulder upto waist and away.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Over joints area and over face Abhyanga is done in circular strokes, soft strokes for face.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Always put some oil inside ears. Scalp and feet should be massaged very well with warm oil.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
Though Abhyanga is described in Diwali in Indian calendar, it should be done every day during winter and at least once in a week in other seasons.
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
Sesame oil should be used during winter because of its higher oil content.
While Coconut oil is ideal for seasons other than winter.
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
So treat yourself with Abhyanga not only in Diwali but regularly.&lt;/p>    
</Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Indian Gooseberry</title>
    <ImagePath>images/GrannyTips/Gooseberry.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Gooseberry</Element>
    <Description>
      Granny Says:- 
      Indian gooseberry known as ‘Amla’ is a wonder medicine in Ayurveda. 
      
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.
    </Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_gooseberry">Indian Gooseberry&lt;/a> known as 'Amla' is a wonder medicine in Ayurveda. Its benefit is not just rich source of vitamin C but also its specific composition , because of which it controls all the 3 elements (Doshas) 'Kapha', 'Pitta' and 'Vaat' in body.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It acts as '&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rasayana">Rasayana&lt;/a>'. The medicines which regularize metabolic activities, improve immunity and strengthen the body are categorized as 'Rasayana'.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Amla is used in many diseases such as Acidity, Colitis, Urinary tract infections, cough, diabetes, wounds. It improves liver function, thus quality of blood and 'Shukra Dhatu' (the reproductive functions.) Other benefits include sharper mind, memory, fairer complexion, youthful and healthy long life. &lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li> As fresh fruits/fruit slices/juice (1-2 tea spoons/day)&lt;/li>
&lt;li> Chyavanprash.&lt;/li>
&lt;li> Moravala (Amla jam).&lt;/li>
&lt;li> As dry powder (choorna).&lt;/li>
&lt;li> In Sherbats and pickles (Eat pickle in moderate quantity). &lt;/li> 
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p> The best time to have Amla is in early morning, empty stomach. Nothing should be had half an hour after that. For best results have it for long duration (every day)
&lt;/p></Content>
  </Item>
</GrannysTips>