<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<SeasonalProblems>
  <Item>
    <title>Summer</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SeasonalProblems/Summer.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Summer</Element>
    <Description>Summer Time !!!
Certain measures that you can take to combat the summer heat and stay healthy this season are described in this section. 
     
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.
    </Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>Summer Time !!!&lt;br/>
Following are certain measures that you can take to combat the summer heat and stay healthy this season&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Drink plenty of liquids like coconut water, sugarcane juice, fruit juice, buttermilk etc.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>At least 10 glasses of water a day is must in this season.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Eat light food.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Avoid hot, spicy, oily meals and opt for foods high in water content including fruits, salads, soups and buttermilk.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Lassi made from churned curd, cream and ginger acts as re-hydrating agent in summer.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A raw mango with salt can quench excessive thirst.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Avoid alcoholic beverages and drinks containing caffeine(tea and coffee) which can make the condition for heat worse.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>While going out use umbrella to block sun rays.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Do outdoor work in the early mornings or late evenings.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Take frequent baths and showers to cool your body and to keep it clean.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Wear light-colored, loose fitting cotton clothes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Smoking can constrict blood vessels and impair the ability to acclimatize to heat, so avoid it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fans blow hot air and increase the amount of evaporation of sweat. So, air conditioners are better.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Monsoon</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SeasonalProblems/Monsoon.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Monsoon</Element>
    <Description>Its Raining... Get your umbrellas and raincoats out.
Beware this is very dagerous season. If you can can stay healthy then only you can enjoy the rains.
      
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.
    </Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>Its Raining... Get your umbrellas and raincoats out.Beware this is very dagerous season. If you can can stay healthy then only you can enjoy the rains.&lt;/p>

&lt;p>From the health point of view beginning and end of the rainy season are very troublesome.The initial days of the monsoon can
cause problems for the body because of the sudden transition of from bone-dry heat to days soaked in a downpour. The
pre-monsoon days packed with clouds causing intense suffocation, resulting in excessive sweating.
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The body is weakened during the summer, as it is the period of dehydration. The digestive power is also weekened. Hence it is
advisable to be moderate regarding diet during the rainy season.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>One should abstain from sleeping during the daytime.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Avoid drinking untreated water as waterborne diseases are at its peak during this season.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Abstain from excercise and moving about in the sun after a spell of rain.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Use of honey liberally in your diet would be very helpful.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If the days are cooler due to heavy rains, one should take diet and drinks that are conspicuously sour, salty, and unctuous.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>One can have fresh and hot vegetable soups.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>One should wear light and clean apparel.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Try to keep your rooms devoid of humidity.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Do not allow water to stagnate in your compound. Such pools are breeding ground for mosquitoes and other insects.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Winter</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SeasonalProblems/Winter.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Winter</Element>
    <Description>Winter is here... Grab your woolen clothes. Its time to flaunt them.
Also follow certain basic steps to be healthy this season.
      
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.
    </Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>Winter is here... Grab your woolen clothes. Its time to flaunt them.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Also follow certain basic steps to be healthy this season.&lt;/p>&lt;p>Our body is programmed to take care of the changes, but occasionally you may have to aid the process of adjustment through food
and suitable alterations in lifestyle. When a cold, dry winds blow, the body sense that something akin to itself has begun to
dominate the scene.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During Winter the digestive system becomes stronger and it can effectively digest large quantities of food.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>One can consume milk, ghee, fat, oils, rice as dietary staples.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Include sour, sweet, salted soup or meat of aquatic and marshy animals in the diet.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Try to include wine, vinegar, and honey in the diet.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Regularly massage the body with oils. Also apply oil on head&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Use room heaters or spend time in heated chambers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Try to expose the body to sun's rays.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Avoid light and cold foods. Also avoid bitter,pungent and stringent tastes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To prevent drying up of the skin, take 100 ml milk, add 5 drops of olive oil and 8 drops of rose water to it. Apply on the skin gently and smoothly. Then expose yourself to mild sun for 10 minutes before a warm water bath.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To keep the face glowing, wash it at-least two times a day with lukewarm water.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Massaging the skin with mustard oil is good for skin during winter. Sunrays will enhance the the good effects if this procedure.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Eat plenty of greens and seasonal fruits since they contain micro and macro elements, which are required for the smooth functioning
of body.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Cream of milk is also good for cracked lips, if used as an application.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Honey is very good natural healer. Apply it over cracked lips after diluting it with double the quantity of water.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
</SeasonalProblems>

