<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<SelfCure>
  <Item>
    <title>Acidity</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Acidity.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Acidity</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
Acidity/Heartburn is due to presence of too much acid in the stomach that causes exasperation of the gastrointestinal casing. This causes a blazing pain. When this excessive acid leaks back into the throat this inflames and the reaction of heartburn is produced.
      
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> -
Acidity/Heartburn is due to presence of too much acid in the stomach that causes exasperation of the gastrointestinal casing. This causes a blazing pain. When this excessive acid leaks back into the throat this inflames and the reaction of heartburn is produced.&lt;/p>
      
&lt;strong>Causes&lt;/strong> -&lt;ul>&lt;li>Consumption of spicy foods&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eating speedily, very fast devoid of proper chewing&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eating hurriedly while beneath stress&lt;/li>&lt;li>Inappropriate sleep&lt;/li>&lt;li>Alcohol utilization&lt;/li>&lt;li>Pregnant women may undergo because when the baby grows, the uterus exerts force on the digestive area&lt;/li>&lt;li>Overweight people may bear because of unnecessary pressure on their digestive tract.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -&lt;ul>&lt;li>Stay away from oil, curd, Buttermilk, sour foods like tamarind, fried foods, pickles, hot spicy foods, vinegar, and chocolate&lt;/li>&lt;li>Stay away from raw salad of vegetables like onion, cabbage, radish, and peppers&lt;/li>&lt;li>Keep away from unripe high pectin fruits, such as unripe apple.&lt;/li>&lt;li>Grind up the food properly. Do not consume in hurry.&lt;/li>&lt;li>Do not bounce meals. Do not keep great gap between meals. This produces gas / current of air.&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink lots of water, at least 8 glasses each day.&lt;/li>&lt;li>Do not eat just before going to bed.&lt;/li>&lt;li>End smoking and cut down on alcohol.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A standard recommendation is to take two teaspoonful of ghee in a glass of warm milk. It could be taken instead of dinner, or two hours after a very light dinner.&lt;/li>&lt;li>A good remedy for acidity is to chew up a few basil (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tulsi">tulsi&lt;/a>) leaves to obtain relief from blazing, nausea and gas.&lt;/li>&lt;li>Coconut water is exceptionally good in this condition.&lt;/li>&lt;li>Stay a small part of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaggery">jaggery&lt;/a> (gur) in your jaws and slowly suck it. Repeat it each hour till acidity subsides.&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat watermelon, banana or cucumber each hour.&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat a few almonds when your experience heartburn symptoms&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink a glass of cold milk for quick relief of heartburn and acidity&lt;/li>&lt;li>Acquire one piece of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clove">clove&lt;/a> and suck on it gradually&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink fresh mint juice gradually after meals.&lt;/li>&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amla">Amla&lt;/a> (Indian gooseberry) in powdered form is also helpful.&lt;/li>&lt;li>Maintaining an standing posture for some time after food will help in preventing reaction&lt;/li>&lt;li>Sleep with your head and shoulder on a elevated pillow for height&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Intestinal Worms</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Intestinal_Worms.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>IntestinalWorms</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
Worms are a common problem for humans across the world and can affect any of us irrespective of age or gender, but the problem is most prevalent among toddlers and children. Worm infestations can in most cases be treated quite easily and effectively with medicated intestinal worms treatments. Worm infestations may not always pose a serious direct risk, but they can cause some serious complications if neglected that may even be life threatening. This is why the problem of parasitic worms should always be treated very seriously.
      
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> - &lt;br/>
Worms are a common problem for humans across the world and can affect any of us irrespective of age or gender, but the problem is most prevalent among toddlers and children. Worm infestations can in most cases be treated quite easily and effectively with medicated intestinal worms treatments. Worm infestations may not always pose a serious direct risk, but they can cause some serious complications if neglected that may even be life threatening. This is why the problem of parasitic worms should always be treated very seriously.&lt;/p>
      
&lt;strong>Symptoms&lt;/strong>:-

&lt;ul>&lt;li>The usual symptoms of intestinal worms are diarrhea, foul breath, dark circles under the eyes, constant desire for food, restlessness at night with bad dreams and headaches.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Worms may give rise to inflammation of the intestine and lungs, nausea, vomiting, loss of weight, fever, nervousness, and irritability.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Causes&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Eating contaminated food.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Worms may enter the body from dirty fingers and food.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Worms may enter the human body through bare foot walking on infected earth.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Worms may be transmitted to the body through undercooked flesh foods or foods contaminated by dogs.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The real cause of intestinal worms, however, is faulty living. The eggs of these worms, taken into the human body through food, and water, can breed in the intestines only if they find there a suitable medium for their propagation. This medium is an intestinal tract clogged with morbid matter.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Personal hygiene and household cleanliness are two ways in which spread of such worms can be prevented.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Wash Hands frequently, especially before meals and after using the toilet.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Keep fingernails short and clean to avoid an infection.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>A tablespoon of freshly ground coconut should be taken at breakfast, followed by 30 to 60 ml of castor oil mixed with 250 to 375 ml of lukewarm milk after three hours. This process may be repeated till the cure is complete.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Worms in children can be eradicated by taking onion juice.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Both fresh garlic and its oil are effective. An ancient method of its administration was to place a couple of cloves fresh garlic in each shoe. As the person walked, the cloves got crushed, and the worm-killing garlic oil was absorbed by the skin and carried by the blood into the intestines easily, as it possessed a powerful penetrative force. This ancient method is worth a trial by those who do no not like the taste of garlic and cannot eat it. Those who can eat raw garlic, however, should chew three cloves of garlic every morning.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Take 4 tablespoonful of the fresh milky juice of unripe papaya fruit with 1 tablespoonful of honey and 4 tablespoonful of boiling water. After two hours a reasonable amount of castor oil with lime juice should be taken.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A small cup of grated carrot taken every morning, with no other food added to the meal, can clear these worms quickly.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Gastritis</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Gastritis.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Gastritis</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
Gastritis is an inflammation, irritation, or erosion of the lining of the stomach. The inflammatory lesions may be either acute (suddenly) or chronic (gradually). Gastritis is actually the medical term for almost any stomach upset, sometimes also referred to as gastroenteritis. If gastritis is left untreated, it can lead to a severe loss in blood, or in some cases increase the risk of developing stomach cancer.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> -&lt;br/>
Gastritis is an inflammation, irritation, or erosion of the lining of the stomach. The inflammatory lesions may be either acute (suddenly) or chronic (gradually). Gastritis is actually the medical term for almost any stomach upset, sometimes also referred to as gastroenteritis. If gastritis is left untreated, it can lead to a severe loss in blood, or in some cases increase the risk of developing stomach cancer.&lt;/p>
      
&lt;strong>Symptoms&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Nausea, Vomiting, Headache, recurrent upset stomach, gas, fever&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Abdominal bloating; a general feeling of uneasiness, Ache and discomfort in the region of the stomach&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Burning or gnawing feeling in the stomach between meals or at night&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Indigestion, Loss of appetite&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Black, tarry stools&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Additional symptoms are a coated tongue, foul breath, bad taste in the mouth, increased flow of saliva, scanty urination and mental depression.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In supplementary chronic cases the patient complaints of heartburn and a feeling of fullness in the abdomen, particularly after meals.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Causes of Gastritis&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Digestive disorders are the main cause of gastritis troubles.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Habitual overeating; eating of poorly combined or improperly cooked food.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Excessive intake of strong tea, coffee, or alcoholic drinks or usual use of large quantities of condiments and sauces.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Worry, anxiety, grief, and prolonged tension, strong acids, and caustic materials.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Regular use of pain killers and non steroidal anti inflammatory drugs.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Avoid excessive use of alcohol and drink only in moderation as alcohol irritates the stomach lining&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Eliminate indigestion by eating several small meals each day rather than 2 or 3 large ones. This helps prevent acid from upsetting your stomach&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Stay away from foods that upset your stomach, especially spicy or deep fried foods&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Quit smoking and avoid secondhand smoke. Smoking irritates the stomach lining making you more susceptible to gastritis and ulcers&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Avoid regular consumption of pain killers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Get yourself down to a healthy weight.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Decrease the stress in your life as much as you can. Stress increases stomach acids and slow down the digestive process. Find some new ways to relax and unwind like walking or yoga.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Coconut water is a superb remedy for gastritis. It provides the stomach with the necessary vitamins and minerals. It helps the stomach in returning to the normal condition.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rice_gruel">Rice gruel&lt;/a> is an excellent remedy for acute cases of gastritis. One cup of rice gruel is recommended two times daily.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Potato juice has been found important in relieving gastritis. The suggested dose is half a cup of the juice, two or three times daily, half an hour before meals.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Curds and cottage cheese should be used generously. Too many dissimilar foods should not be mixed at the same meal. Meals must be taken at least two hours before going to sleep at night.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The patient should ban the use of alcohol, tobacco, spices and condiments, meat, red pepper, sour foods, pickles, strong tea and coffee. He must avoid sweets, pastries, rich cakes, and aerated waters.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Application of heat with a hot compress or hot water bottle, two times daily, either on an empty stomach or two hours after meals, will also be useful.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The patient may assume a fast for two of three days or more, depending on the severity of the condition. He must be given only warm water to drink during this period. This will give rest to the stomach and allow the toxic situation causing the inflammation to subside.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>After the acute signs subside, the patient must adopt an all-fruit diet for the next three days and take juicy fruits such as apples, pears, grapes, grapefruit, oranges, pineapple, peaches, and melons.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Mouth Ulcers</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Mouth_Ulcers.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Ulcers</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
Mouth ulcers are open sores, which appear in the mouth. They are white or yellow in color, and are normally accompanied with a sharp pain, which is felt most when the person is eating. The pain is quite sharp when salty or spicy food passes over the ulcer. Mouth ulcers can occur wherever in the mouth - on the inner surface of the cheeks, lips, tongue, palate and at the base of the gums
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> - &lt;br/>
Mouth ulcers are open sores, which appear in the mouth. They are white or yellow in color, and are normally accompanied with a sharp pain, which is felt most when the person is eating. The pain is quite sharp when salty or spicy food passes over the ulcer. Mouth ulcers can occur wherever in the mouth - on the inner surface of the cheeks, lips, tongue, palate and at the base of the gums
&lt;/p>
&lt;strong>Causes&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Diet may be lacking green or may be anemic&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Digestive problems like constipation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Hormonal imbalances, particularly during puberty or  in girls&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Constant stress&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Genetic factors&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You may be brushing your teeth over-vigorously. Such brushing causes abrasions on the gum that can turn ulcerous.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Irritation by a few chemicals, tobacco or even alcohol&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Illness of the herpes simplex virus&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Avoid hot or spicy food, coffee, tea, alcohol and tobacco.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Have a well balanced diet.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Take more rest.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Avoid sour things, including curd and pickles.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Consuming more green vegetables in the diet helps to be ever protected from ulcers. Greens also provide the essential fiber for the movement of bowels. This avoids constipation.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Mix the skin of a lemon with white &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catechu">catechu&lt;/a>. Grind them into a paste. Apply this straightly on the ulcer. The ulcer will get treated approximately immediately.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mix a ripened banana in curds that have been prepared from cow's milk and eat this as a dessert.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Crush the leaves of the Indian plum (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jambul">jambul&lt;/a>). Give off their paste in water and gargle with this water.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papaya">Papaya&lt;/a> is an extremely good fruit to be consumed when you have mouth ulcers. It soothes the mouth ulcers and helps in their fast recovery. Yam is also useful for mouth ulcer problems.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Turmeric is also a cooling agent as this helps in relieving mouth ulcers. It is mixed in water and the suspension can be used for gargling for mouth ulcers treatment.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It is desirable to stop fatty food - especially that which contains oils - till the time the ulcers have healed.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When ulcers occur in the mouth, hot and spicy food must be stopped instantly. These will make worse the pains of the ulcers. Caffeine and tea must also be closed.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Acne</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Acne.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Acne</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
Acne treatment is the most sought after treatment teenagers. Acne is a general and chronic skin ailment. The lesions are generally found on the skin of the face, neck, chest and shoulders.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> - &lt;br/>
Acne treatment is the most sought after treatment teenagers. Acne is a general and chronic skin ailment. The lesions are generally found on the skin of the face, neck, chest and shoulders.&lt;/p>
     
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Symptoms&lt;/strong> - &lt;br/>
Acne symptoms include the presence of different types of pimples and cysts on the affected area of the skin.&lt;/p>
     
&lt;strong>Causes&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Teenagers and young adolescents show an increased manifestation of acne as the hormonal changes during puberty add to the sebum build-up, leading to more inflamed pores.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>In girls and women, the timeline during the menstrual cycle shows an increase in acne on the skin.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Hormonal changes at the onset of puberty or during pregnancy can also cause the pores on the skin to get clogged up.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>A sudden start or stop in the use of birth control medication can also result in acne showing up on the skin.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Lifestyle changes, especially being subject to a lot of stress, can also result in acne developing on the skin.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Heredity and the use of greasy cosmetics also results in the appearance of acne.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Expose your body to sun and air, but do not sunburn.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Fresh air and daily exercise are very important. Get sufficient sleep. Keep your bowels regular.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Keep your bedsheets clean as dead skin, oil, cosmetics, hair, dirt on the sheets will clog your pores further.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Wash your face twice or thrice a day. Avoid using soaps that dry your skin.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid oil-based cosmetics, as they tend to clog the pores on your skin.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Wash your hair every third or fourth day.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>
 
&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Apply an ice cube (wrapped in as soft piece of cloth) wherever you spot redness. It not only reduces the redness, it lessens the inflammation and helps the skin heal.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Do not pinch the pimple as it can lead to inflammation and can leave scars on your face. However, if you are desperate, then use a hot, clean cloth or tissue to soften the pimple. This will allow you to break the pimple open with gentle pressure.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Clean your skin thoroughly and apply egg white with cotton swab. Let it stay for several hours or overnight. Egg white acts as an astringent.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>To treat affected area make infusion of basil (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tulasi">Tulasi&lt;/a>) leaves. Put 2 to 4 tsps.  of dried basil leaves in a cup of boiling water, steep for 10 minutes, cool, and apply.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Place turmeric powder or basil leaves in a bowl of water, which has just been boiled. Cover your hair with a towel. Create a mini-steam bath for your face. Make sure to wash your face immediately afterwards, as dirt and oil can be removed more easily from open pores.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Apply lemon juice and rose water in equal amount with a cotton ball and leave for half an hour and wash. Repeat this remedy for 20-25 days.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Mix 3-4 drops of lemon juice in 1 tablespoon of sour cream, 1 tablespoon of yogurt and 1 tablespoon of grind oatmeal. Apply on face; leave the paste for 10-15 minutes and wash.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Take small amount of ground almonds and honey and make a fine paste. Gently massage this paste on your face with a hot washcloth and then rinse with cold water.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Mix 1/2 cup mashed apple, 1/2 cup cooked oatmeal, 1 slightly beaten egg white and 1 tablespoon lemon juice into a fine paste and apply to your face for at least 15 minutes to 20 minutes and rinse with cold water.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>An 'all-fruit' diet for a week, taking three meals a day, of fresh ripe fruits, such as apples, pears, grapes, grapefruit, pineapples, and peaches is recommended. Merely unsweetened lemon or plain water, either hot or cold, ought to be drunk.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Following the one-week, all-fruit diet, the patient can increasingly adopt a well-balanced diet with stress on raw foods, in particular fresh fruit and vegetables, sprouted seeds, raw nuts, and wholegrain cereals, mainly millet and brown rice. Additional short periods of the 'all-fruit' diet meant for three days or so might be essential at a monthly period till the skin's state improves.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Meats, sugar, strong tea or coffee, condiments, pickles, soft drinks, candies, ice cream, developed and processed foods be supposed to be avoided as far as possible&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Eczema</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Eczema.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Eczema</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
Eczema also called as dermatitis, is a group of skin disorders which can affect all age groups. The severity of this disease can vary. In more than 90% of cases, eczema is found to happen in children below 5 years of age. It is a non-contagious ailment.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> - &lt;br/>
Eczema also called as dermatitis, is a group of skin disorders which can affect all age groups. The severity of this disease can vary. In more than 90% of cases, eczema is found to happen in children below 5 years of age. It is a non-contagious ailment.&lt;/p>
&lt;strong>Symptoms&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Itching
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Redness on skin
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Dry and flaky skin
&lt;/li>&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blister">Itchy blisters&lt;/a>
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Inflammation on skin
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Small bumps on forehead, neck and cheek
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Rough and thickened skin.&lt;/ul>&lt;/li>

&lt;strong>Causes&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Eczema is measured to be hereditary. Studies reveal that a person is prone to eczema if his family has a history of directly linked conditions like hay fever and asthma.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Irritants like smoke, chemicals, detergents, solvents and so on, could aggravate eczema. Even weather circumstances could aggravate the condition. Extreme stress, heat and emotional stress also aggravates the symptoms of eczema.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Some time blood circulation problem in the leg can also cause eczema.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Lack of vitamin B6 causes eczema.&lt;/ul>&lt;/li>

&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Prevent dry skin by taking warm (not hot) showers rather than baths. Use a mild soap or body cleanser. Dry yourself very carefully and apply moisturizing skin lotions all over your body. Avoid lotions with fragrances or other irritating substances.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid wearing tight-fitting, rough, or scratchy clothing.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid scratching the rash. If you can't stop yourself from scratching, cover the area with a dressing. Wear gloves at night to minimize skin damage from scratching.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Anything that causes sweating can irritate the rash. Avoid strenuous exercise during a flare.&lt;/ul>&lt;/li>

&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Apply a mixture of 1-teaspoon camphor and 1 teaspoon sandalwood paste on the itchiness.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Apply &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nutmeg">nutmeg&lt;/a> paste carefully to the affected areas.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Zinc taken orally and applied straightly on the affected skin is effective.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Together shark cartilage and lotion of blueberry leaves reduce inflammation.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink tomato juice every day, it will cure the symptoms in a few days.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>If you are allergic or susceptible to certain foods then try avoiding them, because they can trigger eczema. Dairy products, eggs, nuts, preservatives and citrus fruits are more expected to trigger &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eczema">eczema&lt;/a>.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Forever avoid substances you are allergic to.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Wear mostly cotton clothes, as they do not irritate your itchy skin. Stay away from wool clothes and blankets.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Take light diet.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid cutting of vegetables especially garlic, onion, tomatoes, and ladies finger. Also avoid peeling of oranges.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>The other offending substances are rubber footwear, spectacle frames, furs, artificial jewelry, and synthetic clothes.&lt;/ul>&lt;/li></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Age spots</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Age_spots.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>AgeSpots</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
Age spots are the yellowish-brown flat spots that look like large freckles and are thought to be caused by aging, too much sun, impaired liver function, and a dietary or nutritional deficiency.  As we age, our metabolism changes and the liver may become so over-loaded with toxins that it cannot get rid of them. Result is age spots. They take years to form and eliminating them takes time too.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>
&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Improve your diet to include fruits and vegetables, especially in raw form.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink 8 to 10 glasses of water daily.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid sweets, caffeine, alcohol, tobacco, and junk foods.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid rancid oils. Refrigerate all after opening.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Have nuts and seeds stored in freezer or refrigerator. Store grains in cool places.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid all fried foods as the hot cooking oils contain substances that damage the skin.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Take &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beta-Carotene">beta-carotene&lt;/a> rich foods such as carrots, spinach, sweet-potatoes, pumpkin, mango, cauliflower etc.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Take potassium-rich foods like banana, potato, coconut-water, cur, soybeans, orange, pumpkin, sweet potato, almonds, spinach, ground nuts etc.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Wheat flour, chicken liver, oysters, sunflower seeds etc. contain reasonable amounts of selenium which will also help in this condition.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Consume Vitamin E rich foods like almonds, cashew nuts, groundnuts, soya beans, sunflower oil, sesame oil, groundnut oil etc. Vitamin E is an antioxidant that slows aging and aids in tissue repair.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Zinc is important for your skin’s health. Meat and poultry are generally high in zinc. Also include &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guava">guava&lt;/a>, papaya, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_gooseberry">Indian gooseberry&lt;/a>, grapes, oranges, tomatoes, and such vitamin C rich foodstuffs in your diet.
&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Rubbing fresh &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aloe_vera">aloe-Vera&lt;/a> juice or gel on the spots will help fade them. Use the gel twice a day for a month or two.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Dab buttermilk on the spots. The lactic acid and other ingredients in the milk are beneficial to the skin.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Gas/Flatulence</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Gas.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Gas</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
Gas/Flatulence is the emission of a mixture of gases called 'flatus' present in the intestine. This gas is produced by symbiotic bacteria and yeasts found in the gastrointestinal tract. Flatus is usually released under pressure through the anus which creates sound and is often accompanied by a foul odor.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> - &lt;br/>
Gas/Flatulence is the emission of a mixture of gases called 'flatus' present in the intestine. This gas is produced by symbiotic bacteria and yeasts found in the gastrointestinal tract. Flatus is usually released under pressure through the anus which creates sound and is often accompanied by a foul odor.&lt;/p>
      
&lt;strong>Symptoms&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Heartburn
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Indigestion
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Regurgitation
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Pain and discomfort in the upper abdomen, Bloating
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Nausea
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Difficulty in swallowing
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Hoarseness and coughing
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Dental erosion&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>
&lt;strong>Causes of Gas/&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flatulence">Flatulence&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Presence of excessive amounts of bacteria in the intestines
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Consumption of large amounts of fibrous foods
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Consumption of products that contain malt extracts
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Digestive disorders such as gastroenteritis
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Irregular bowel movements or constipation
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Food or water that may be prepared under unhygienic conditions
&lt;/li>&lt;li>A high-fat diet generates a huge amount of carbon dioxide, some of which is released as flatulence or gas
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Odorous flatulence is caused due to the metabolic breakdown of sulfur-containing proteins and amino acids in the intestines
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Persistent bloating and flatulence that is present consistently over a period may be an indication of a serious medical condition such as colorectal cancer. This may need deeper investigation and treatment&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>
     
&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Eliminate certain foods and beverages such as fatty, spicy foods, milk, coffee, tomatoes, oranges, peppermint, chocolate and alcohol that may trigger stomach reflux symptoms
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat smaller meals throughout the day and avoid overeating
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat slowly and always sit up straight when eating
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid going to bed on a full stomach – eat meals 2-3 hours before lying down
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Wear loose fitting clothes to release pressure on your stomach
&lt;/li>&lt;li>If you are overweight, lose some weight to relieve symptoms
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Stop smoking
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Reduce stress levels by exercising, practicing deep breathing exercises or meditating
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Elevate the head of your bed by placing blocks or a bed wedges under the bedposts to alleviate gastric reflux&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>
     
&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Eating &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carom_seed">Carom seed&lt;/a> and black salt with hot water gives immediate relief
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink hot water with Lemon juice, Ginger piece and Black pepper powder
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Boil 5-6 Cloves in water. Drink this after cooling
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Chew on a piece of Ginger before meals as it improves digestion and helps in reducing gas formation
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Use Asafoetida, Fenugreek seeds, Cumin seeds, Carom seeds, Ginger, Garlic regularly in cooking
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Sitting for 5 minutes in an upright posture after every meal gives instant and permanent relief
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Take Roasted &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cumin">Cumin&lt;/a> powder with Honey after meals
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat a piece of Jaggery after every meal
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Sprouted &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fenugreek_seed">fenugreek seed&lt;/a> or drink salted Buttermilk with Fenugreek seeds
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink Mint Juice, Bitter gourd Juice, Cabbage juice or Carrot juice
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eating Orange in the morning cleans the intestine thereby reducing gas formation or eating Orange with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_salt">Black salt&lt;/a> gives instant relief
&lt;/li>&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asafoetida">Asafoetida&lt;/a> paste applied on the naval gives instant relief&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>
</Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Obesity</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Obesity.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Obesity</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
Obesity is a physical condition that occurs from excessive storage of fat in the body. Obesity has been defined as a weight more than 20% above what is measured usual as per the body mass index, which is calculated from an individual's age, height, and weight. Excess of fatty tissues results in obesity and causes fitness disorders. One of the places where the excessive body fat can easily be seen is around the waistline. A waist measurement of 40-45 inches or more in men and 35 inches or more in women is linked to an amplified risk for heart disease and other health problems associated with obesity. 
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> - &lt;br/>
Obesity is a physical condition that occurs from excessive storage of fat in the body. Obesity has been defined as a weight more than 20% above what is measured usual as per the body mass index, which is calculated from an individual's age, height, and weight. Excess of fatty tissues results in obesity and causes fitness disorders. One of the places where the excessive body fat can easily be seen is around the waistline. A waist measurement of 40-45 inches or more in men and 35 inches or more in women is linked to an amplified risk for heart disease and other health problems associated with obesity. &lt;/p>
      
&lt;strong>Symptoms&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>High blood pressure
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Type 2 diabetes
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Gallbladder disease
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Some types of cancer
&lt;/li>&lt;li>High cholesterol
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Sleeping and breathing problems
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Shortness of breath with exertion
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Depression or other emotional problems
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Difficulty in walking or moving around
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Heartburn
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Rashes in the folds of the skin
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Snoring&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Causes of Obesity&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Overeating and an Inactive or Sedentary lifestyle 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Genetic disorders 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Binge eating disorder, little exercise and crash diets all slow down the metabolism and make weight loss difficult
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Weight cycling, caused by repeated attempts to lose weight by dieting 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Some people overeat because of stress, depression, hopelessness, anger, boredom, and many other reasons that have nothing to do with hunger
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Insufficient sleep 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Underlying illness such as hypothyroidism
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Certain medications such as atypical antipsychotics
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Smoking cessation 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>While weight gain during pregnancy is expected and essential for a healthy baby, many women struggle to lose weight after childbirth, commonly referred to as 'pregnancy weight'&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Limit the intake of fried foods which are rich in fat. Instead, broil or bake your food
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Limit meat intake to once every day. Prefer to eat poultry and fish over other meat items
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat enough portions from all major food groups to ensure your diet is rich in nutrition
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Do not keep any stock of junk food in your home
&lt;/li>&lt;li>If you do not feel hungry at regular meal time, then cut down your portion size and eat just enough food to keep you satiated and energetic for your daily tasks
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Reduce the consumption of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monosodium_glutamate">monosodium glutamate&lt;/a> (MSG) and salt
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Cut down on the sugar
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink plenty of water every day to flush out toxins and impurities from your system
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Do not consume more than four eggs a week as these are high in cholesterol
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Limit intake of desserts and similar high-calorie items which are low in nutrition
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink alcohol in moderation or avoid it altogether
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Do at least 30 minutes of moderate physical activity every day, practice yoga, meditation or other self-awareness techniques to improve your self-control&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bitter_gourd">Bitter gourd&lt;/a> juice taken in the morning can do wonders
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink Spinach juice and lemon juice daily
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink Buttermilk everyday
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eating raw tomatoes and Onion with a pinch of Salt everyday helps to remove extra fat
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat ten raw Sweet neem leaves everyday
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat Radish, cucumber, raw  cabbage daily
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Substitute Rice and wheat with Ragi
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat Drumstick or Drumstick leaves regularly in meals
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Chew Garlic everyday in the empty stomach with a spoon of honey
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat only fruit diet one day in a week
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Massage the body and take steam bath at least once in a week
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Do regular exercise like long walks in the morning and evening, yoga and other physical exercise&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Common Cold</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Common_Cold.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>CommonCold</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
A common cold is rightly termed so because of the multiple kinds of colds that an individual goes through in his/her lifetime. Common colds are often a very mild viral infection that clears up after it has run its course. In isolated incidents, common colds can increase in severity and may lead to advanced infections like bronchitis or pneumonia. 
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> -
A common cold is rightly termed so because of the multiple kinds of colds that an individual goes through in his/her lifetime. Common colds are often a very mild viral infection that clears up after it has run its course. In isolated incidents, common colds can increase in severity and may lead to advanced infections like bronchitis or pneumonia. &lt;/p>
    
&lt;strong>Symptoms&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Running nose, Sneezing, Congestion of the nasal passages
&lt;/li>&lt;li>An itchy and sore throat
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Change in speech, which becomes quite hoarse and/or nasal
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Watering of the eyes
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Headache, Bodyache
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Fever that is low grade in nature
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Overall feeling of fatigue&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Causes of Common Cold&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Close contact with an infected individual puts you at high risk of picking up the infection, particularly if your immunity is low
&lt;/li>&lt;li>People who have a chronic medical condition are also susceptible to colds as their immune system is quite compromised
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Low strength, exposure to cold, lack of sleep, mental depression, fatigue, and factors such as sudden modifications in temperature, dust and other irritating inhalations are important contributory causes&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Wash your hands often. You can also carry a small tube of hand sanitizer or sanitizing hand wipes when visiting public places
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid touching your face, especially the nose, mouth, and eye areas, if you are around someone with a cold or have been touching surfaces in a public area
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Don't smoke. It increases susceptibility to colds and other infections
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Keep household surfaces clean. Wipe these surfaces frequently with soap and water or a disinfectant solution
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Use paper towels in the kitchen and bathroom for hand washing. Germs can live for several hours on cloth towels. Alternatively, have separate towels for each family member and provide a clean one for guests
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Throw tissues away after use
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Try to use disposable items if someone in your family is infected
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Maintain a healthy lifestyle
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Control stress. People experiencing emotional stress, have a weak immune system&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Take  Steam inhalation with Eucalyptus oil drops
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Take Black pepper powder, Ginger juice and Basil juice mixed with Honey  thrice a day
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink Tea with a few Mint leaves or Ginger or Basil leaves
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Saline gargles are helpful to soothe an itchy and sore throat
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Put few drops of Fresh neem leaves juice in the nostrils
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Vitamin C deficiency can often cause Cold problems. So go for rich natural source of vitamin C like Oranges, Gooseberries, Sweet lime, lemon, Grapes, Guava etc
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eating a small piece of Onion (pea size) or sucking a piece of Clove (Laung) helps to get instant relief
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat an Apple every day before meals
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Consume a hot glass of turmeric and ginger mixed in milk
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink hot water with Lemon juice and Honey
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink a decoction of Tamarind leaves boiled in water for few minutes and filtered
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Have soup made from Tamarind pulp&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Sinusitis</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Sinusitis.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Sinusitis</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
Sinusitis refers to an inflammation of the mucus membrane lining the paranasal sinuses. It often follows a common cold, influenza, and other general infections. Infecting germs sometimes find their way into sinuses or chambers on either side of the nasal passage, leading to sinus trouble. The sinuses are basically moist air passages that are hollowed out in the facial bones, behind and around the nasal area
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> - &lt;br/>
Sinusitis refers to an inflammation of the mucus membrane lining the para-nasal sinuses. It often follows a common cold, influenza, and other general infections. Infecting germs sometimes find their way into sinuses or chambers on either side of the nasal passage, leading to sinus trouble. The sinuses are basically moist air passages that are hollowed out in the facial bones, behind and around the nasal area&lt;/p>
      
&lt;strong>Symptoms&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Pain or pressure in the forehead, eyes or cheeks
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Post nasal drip
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Stuffy nose, Runny nose, Sneezing, difficulty in breathing
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Fever, Headache
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Lack of appetite
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Sore throat
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Aching in the upper teeth
&lt;/li>&lt;li>A cold that seems to get better, then worsens&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Causes of Sinusitis&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Excessive mucus production, resulting in blockage of the sinuses, which could be caused by a cold or allergies
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Bacterial or viral infection, especially after you have a cold
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Allergy attack
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Changes in temperature, Air pressure
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Pollution, Chemical fumes
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Smoking
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Swimming or diving
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Excessive use of decongestant nasal sprays.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Treating allergies and colds 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Moisten the air in your home. Humidifiers can better increase moisture in the air of your home. Air conditioners are also good way of stabilizing the temperature in either high or low weather. 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid pollution 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eliminate smoking habits and alcohol consumption
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Reduce air travel 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink lots of water. Water increases the amount of moisture in the body
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid swimming, Refrain from diving 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Good hygiene, such as frequent hand wash with soap and water. 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Minimize consumption of dairy products 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Take many hot showers and inhale steam 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid temperature extremes 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Get an influenza vaccine each year
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat plenty of fruits and vegetables that are rich in antioxidants
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Reduce stress&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Consume a decoction of a tsp of fenugreek seeds boiled in half a glass of water
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Steam Inhalation with Eucalyptus oil drops is effective in curing sinusitis. It opens the nasal passage by draining the sinuses and making mucous flow easy
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Inhale the smell of pungent smelling vegetables, like onion and garlic. Chop fresh garlic and add it to a bowl of hot water for inhaling its steam 2-3 times in a day
&lt;/li>&lt;li>A teaspoon of black cumin seeds tied in a thin cotton cloth can provide relief when inhaled
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Use pure neem oil as nasal drops to get relief
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Gargle with salted lukewarm water
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Prepare ginger or &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cinnamon">cinnamon&lt;/a> tea and drink it when it is slightly on the hotter side
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Carrot juice, taken separately or in combination with juices of beet and cucumber, or with spinach juice, has been found beneficial
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Make a paste of cinnamon and water and apply it on the forehead
&lt;/li>&lt;li>A paste of basil leaves, cloves and dried ginger, when applied on the forehead relieves &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sinus">sinus&lt;/a> infection
&lt;/li>&lt;li>The liberal use of mangoes during the season is considered an effective remedy for prevention and treatment of sinusitis&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
   <Item>
    <title>Tonsillitis</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Tonsillitis.png</ImagePath>
     <Element>Tonsillitis</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
Tonsillitis refers to acute inflammation of the tonsils, which lie, one on each side of the throat. The tonsils are part of the immune system and protect against germs by producing antibodies. These antibodies play an important role in the body’s immune system by attacking bacteria and viruses. However, during this process of protecting the body, the tonsils may also become inflamed or infected.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> -
Tonsillitis refers to acute inflammation of the tonsils, which lie, one on each side of the throat. The tonsils are part of the immune system and protect against germs by producing antibodies. These antibodies play an important role in the body’s immune system by attacking bacteria and viruses. However, during this process of protecting the body, the tonsils may also become inflamed or infected.&lt;/p>

&lt;strong>Symptoms&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Mild or severe sore throat that may develop gradually or suddenly
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Pain and Difficulty in swallowing food or your own saliva
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Fever, vomiting
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Enlarged, tender glands in the jaw and neck
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Loss of voice
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Headache, Earache, General aches and pain
&lt;/li>&lt;li>There is also likely to be some accumulation of pus or a pasty and foul smelling infected material on the pits of the tonsils, Foul smelling breath.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Causes of Tonsillitis&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>A prolonged sore throat caused by an infection could at times develop into tonsillitis
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Constant dry cough
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Forcible and constant use of voice - often at a high pitch
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Chronic Congestion, blockade of nose
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Excessive use of spices, condiments, acrid, pungent and astringent food items
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Excessive eating of toffees, sweets, tamarind, tartaric acid, chewing gum etc.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>
 
&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Wash your hands thoroughly with warm water and soap to prevent the spread of germs
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Cough and sneeze into a tissue to prevent germs from spreading
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat healthy, balanced meals that include all the food groups
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink plenty of water to rid the body’s system of unwanted toxins and detox every once in a while
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Do not share personal items such as toothbrushes, drinking glasses or eating utensils with others
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid close contact with those who are infected with tonsillitis
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Increase your intake of vitamins to strengthen your immune system
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Don’t smoke, as this increases the risk of developing tonsillitis&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>
   
&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>A fresh lime squeezed in a glass of warm water, with four teaspoons of honey and a quarter teaspoon of common salt, should be sipped slowly in such cases
&lt;/li>&lt;li>A glass of pure boiled milk, mixed with a pinch uf turmeric powder and pepper powder, should be taken every night for three nights in the treatment of this condition
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Juices of carrot, beet, and cucumber, taken individually or in combination, when used in combination the proportions are 300 ml of carrot juice, 100 ml of beet juice, and 100 ml of cucumber juice
&lt;/li>&lt;li>A gargle made from fenugreek seeds is very effective
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Gargle with salted lukewarm water
&lt;/li>&lt;li>A paste can be prepared from water and boiled figs and this paste can be applied externally on the throat area to provide a cooling and soothing effect.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Nose Bleeding</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Nose_Bleeding.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>NoseBleeding</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
A nosebleed can be a rather frightening experience, not just for children, but also for adults. However, even though it may not seem so, nosebleeds are rarely serious and can be managed easily. They are fairly common in children, as well as grownups.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> - &lt;br/>
A nosebleed can be a rather frightening experience, not just for children, but also for adults. However, even though it may not seem so, nosebleeds are rarely serious and can be managed easily. They are fairly common in children, as well as grownups.&lt;/p>

&lt;strong>Symptoms&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>The appearance of blood from either one or both the nostrils 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>The necessity to swallow frequently, because of a blocked feeling in the nasal passages 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>The sensation of a fluid at the back of the nose and the throat 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Difficulties in breathing, where you may feel that you are choking a bit
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Appearance of a nasal deformity 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Bleeding in the gums 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Disturbances in vision 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Dizziness or lightheadedness 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Facial pain, accompanied by numbness in the area 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Fainting spells 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Hearing problems 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>High fever and chills 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seizures">Seizures&lt;/a> 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Swelling around the nose or the cheeks 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Vomiting, especially if there are traces of blood in it &lt;/li>&lt;/ul>
      
&lt;strong>Causes of Nose Bleeding&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Nasal or sinus infections 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Foreign objects stuck in the nasal passages 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Infections in the nose and nasal passages 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Nasal surgery
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Exposure to dry and warm air for a long period of time 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Sneezing excessively or blowing the nose too vigorously 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Perforation or deviation in the nasal septum 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Use of certain medications or illegal drugs like cocaine 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Presence of kidney diseases or liver diseases 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Vascular formations in the nose 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Tumors in the nasal passages 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>High blood pressure, accompanied by excess levels of anxiety 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Clotting disorders that may run in the family 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Leukemia 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Exposure to chemical irritants like ammonia 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Common colds 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Excessive use of nasal sprays 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Alcohol abuse 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nasal_polyps">Nasal polyps&lt;/a> 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atherosclerosis">Atherosclerosis&lt;/a>, which is a disease of the arteries 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Exposure to sudden altitude changes, as when flying&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>
      
How to avoid:-
&lt;ul>&lt;li>If you are prone to nosebleeds, check the humidity in your house, and increase it to the normal range
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Keep nostrils moist. Take a shower and breathe deeply to get moisture into your nose. Then put petroleum jelly on the inside of the nose to keep it moist. A saline solution spray will also help
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Daily consumption of citrus fruit can help eliminate recurring nosebleeds.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Make sure you do not have high blood pressure
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid foods that may give you a severe allergic reaction
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Putting a few drops of castor oil, vitamin E or zinc oxide in your nose each day will prevent recurring nosebleeds
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Don't pick your nose with sharp objects&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>
      
Self Help:-
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Apply an icepack or a few cubes of ice in a towel directly to the nose and use it for at least 5 minutes or so. Alternately, a bag of frozen vegetables will also do 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Putting wet cloth on the head is a good remedy to stop nose bleeding
&lt;/li>&lt;li>It is best to keep your head elevated at least till the bleeding stops
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Dip a small piece of cotton in a bit of white vinegar and plug it into the nostril that is bleeding
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Putting a drop of Lemon juice in both the nostrils, helps to stop nose bleeding immediately
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Put drops of juice of Neem or Basil or Onion or sweet grape or pomegranate in the nostrils stop nose bleeding
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Make a solution with water and baking soda and spray 2 to 3 puffs of it on the nose
&lt;/li>&lt;li>The juice squeezed out of Black Cotton leaves applied on the center of the head, stops nose bleeding 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eating a piece of Coconut everyday on empty stomach, helps to overcome nose bleeding
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Apply a paste of Black gram ground with water on the forehead
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Soak  two &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Figs">Figs&lt;/a> in water overnight and eat them with water in the morning&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Varicose Veins</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Varicose_Veins.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>VericoseVeins</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
If you have noticed blue or purplish protruding veins running down your legs you probably suffer from varicose veins. The condition is a lot more prevalent among older individuals, and is unlikely to affect teenagers or young adults. Women are also a lot more susceptible to varicose veins, especially during pregnancy, pre-menstruation and menopause. Men are more likely to suffer from testicular varicose veins, which is one of the leading causes of male infertility.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> -
If you have noticed blue or purplish protruding veins running down your legs you probably suffer from varicose veins. The condition is a lot more prevalent among older individuals, and is unlikely to affect teenagers or young adults. Women are also a lot more susceptible to varicose veins, especially during pregnancy, pre-menstruation and menopause. Men are more likely to suffer from testicular varicose veins, which is one of the leading causes of male infertility.&lt;/p>
      
&lt;strong>Symptoms&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Change in the color of the veins, as they become bluish or even dark purple
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Twisting and bulging of the veins on the legs
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Muscle cramping, burning, swelling and throbbing in the lower leg 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>A feeling of tiredness in the legs behind the knees
&lt;/li>&lt;li>A heavy and achy feeling in the legs
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Intense pain, which could worsen upon sitting 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Appearance of skin ulcers, mainly around the ankle area 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Itchiness around the veins&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Causes of Varicose Veins&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Increased pressure on the veins could cause them to enlarge and bulge
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Weakness in the walls of the veins
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Formation of blood clots in the veins, which obstruct the flow of blood 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Genetics and heredity factors
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Obesity or being overweight significantly increase the amount of pressure exerted on the veins 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Congenital abnormalities in the veins 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Spending a long period of time in one position, which restricts the flow of blood&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Getting an adequate amount of exercise each day 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Shedding the extra pounds, to reduce the pressure on the legs and the feet 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Wearing appropriate footwear; tight fitting or high heeled shoes are best avoided 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Improving the circulation of blood in the legs, by moving around or keeping the legs elevated for short periods of time at regular intervals
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Try to avoid sitting with your legs crossed
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid prolonged standing
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Quit smoking&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>


&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>The simplest of the natural remedies for varicose veins are raw vegetable juices. Especially helpful is the combination of carrot and spinach
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Resting your leg (on a pillow) above hip level
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Wearing supportive stockings they stop the blood from gathering and clotting in small blood vessels. Instead they push the blood towards larger veins, which easily pump the blood to the heart
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Alternating between hot and cold baths proves to be effective against varicose veins
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Add Epsom salts to the bath water as they help strengthen the veins and boost blood circulation
&lt;/li>&lt;li>It is important to include Vitamin E and C to your diet
&lt;/li>&lt;li>It is also beneficial to apply Vitamin E oil to the affected areas
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Apply apple cider vinegar on the skin around the affected area. This helps relieve pain and inflammation
&lt;/li>&lt;li>The marigold extract is an excellent solution for inflamed and ulcerated skin. Apply the extract externally over the enlarged network of veins&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Migraine</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Migraine.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Migraine</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
A migraine is a severe, painful headache that is often preceded or accompanied by sensory warning signs such as flashes of light, blind spots, tingling in the arms and legs, nausea, vomiting, and increased sensitivity to light and sound. The excruciating pain that migraines bring can last for hours or even days. Migraines are about three times more common in women than in men.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> - &lt;br/>
A migraine is a severe, painful headache that is often preceded or accompanied by sensory warning signs such as flashes of light, blind spots, tingling in the arms and legs, nausea, vomiting, and increased sensitivity to light and sound. The excruciating pain that migraines bring can last for hours or even days. Migraines are about three times more common in women than in men.&lt;/p>

&lt;strong>Symptoms&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Pain on one side of the head and often starts from behind the eye
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Pulsating or throbbing pain, nausea and vomiting. You can feel the blood pulsating through the affected side of the head
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Changes in vision such as seeing flashes of light, blind spots or blurry vision
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Strong and painful reactions to light and loud noises
&lt;/li>&lt;li>The simple act of moving may be difficult during the migraine attack. Pain may worsen from activity
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Numbness and weakness or an arm or a leg. In some cases the entire face and tongue may get numb making the speech slurry
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Digestive problems are experienced sometimes as the headache develops
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Irritability, Laziness, Stiff Neck, Stuffy Nose,  Drowsiness, Constipation
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Confused thinking, Difficulty in concentrating&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Causes of Migraine&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Dehydration, Skipping meals or fasting
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Fatigue, Stress, Tension, Depression or Anxiety
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Intense physical activity
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Changes in the physical environment such as changes in season, temperature or altitude
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Various sensory stimuli such as bright lights, flashing lights, unusual smells and loud noise
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Changes in sleeping patterns, sleep disorders or lack of sleep
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Poor posture, Neck or Shoulder tension
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Alcohol and Tobacco smoke
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Certain foods like Chocolate, Cheese, Citrus fruits, Alcohol, Beans, Nuts, Breads and other baked foods, raisins, Caffeine etc
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Hormonal changes (many women experience migraines during their menstrual cycle, menopause or pregnancy)
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Several prescription and non-prescription medications can aggravate migraines&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Eat a healthy, balanced diet and do not skip meals
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Exercise regularly. Exercise can help to reduce tension and stress and lower the chances of migraines
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Try stick to a regular sleeping pattern, and ensure that you get enough sleep each night
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Learn to relax. Practice relaxation techniques and deep breathing (Yoga)
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid tobacco smoke and limit your caffeine intake
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid direct Sunlight
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Keep a migraine journal to help identify migraine triggers. Include all the foods, activities or anything else you did that day. Once you know your triggers then you can do your best to avoid them
&lt;/li>&lt;li>If you are a woman suffering from regular migraines, it may be useful to limit your estrogen intake (birth control pills or hormone replacement therapy)&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Massage head with Castor oil and put a wet cloth on the forehead
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Lemon peel is helpful in solving migraine headache. Grind lemon peel to form a paste and apply it on the forehead. Let it dry and then rinse off with cool water
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Dry Ginger mixed in water can be smelled and applied on the forehead 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Crush a few Cabbage leaves, place it in a cloth and apply on the forehead
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Massaging the forehead with primrose oil is beneficial in curing migraine
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Take some sandalwood powder and add a few drops of water to it, so as to form a paste. Apply this paste on the forehead and let it dry. Once dry, rub it off by hand and wash it.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Hot foot bath, Fomentation over the stomach and spine
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink water regularly and in good quantity. Eat frequent smaller meals than lesser large meals
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink a mixture of Carrot juice, either with Spinach, Beet or Cucumber juice
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat a spoon of Honey, or honey mixed with basil juice
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat Goose berries, Apples with Salt
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eating some sweet, Sugar or Jaggery during Migraine reduces pain in some people instantly
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Chew on some Black pepper, Garlic or raw Onions
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Put Drum stick leaves juice in the nostrils (If you are having pain on the left side put it in the right nostril and vice versa)
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Put few drops of Almond oil in the nostrils&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Vertigo</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Vertigo.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Vertigo</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
Vertigo is a sensation that everything around you is spinning or moving, which is usually caused by a problem in the inner ear, but can also be caused by vision problems. People with vertigo commonly feel things are moving when they are standing completely still and everything around them is still. Vertigo is more severe than dizziness. People with vertigo may find it harder to move around because the spinning sensation tends to affect balance.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> - &lt;br/>
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vertigo">Vertigo&lt;/a> is a sensation that everything around you is spinning or moving, which is usually caused by a problem in the inner ear, but can also be caused by vision problems. People with vertigo commonly feel things are moving when they are standing completely still and everything around them is still. Vertigo is more severe than dizziness. People with vertigo may find it harder to move around because the spinning sensation tends to affect balance.&lt;/p>

&lt;strong>Symptoms&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>A sensation that everything around you is moving or spinning
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Abnormal movement in the eye 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Loss of balance, Lightheadedness
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Blurred vision and other vision problems 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Walking problems, Problem in standing still properly
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Hearing loss and ringing sensation 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Nausea and vomiting 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Perspiration or sweating 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Difficulties in speaking normally
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Reduction in the levels of consciousness or complete loss of consciousness 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Weakness&lt;/li>&lt;/ul> 

&lt;strong>Causes of Vertigo&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>The sensation of motion initiated by sudden head movements or moving the head in a certain direction, Neck Injury
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Inflammation within the inner ear
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Fluctuating pressure of inner ear fluid
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Decreased blood flow to the base of the brain
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Migraine
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Motion Sickness
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Vertigo may also occur as a side effect of some types of medication&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Perform eye exercises. These include looking up and down, side-to-side, and from near to far. Begin slowly and gradually build up speed
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Move your head to the front and back and turn it from side to side beginning slowly and building up speed
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Change body positions. Move from sitting to standing
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Therapeutic exercises
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid fast or sudden body movements
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Do not exercise with full stomach&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Keep still, don't try to read, and avoid bright lights. Slowly resume normal activity after an attack to allow your body to gradually adjust to movement again
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Breathe deeply and slowly
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Take small sips of water
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Soak 1 tsp of Gooseberry powder along with 1 tsp Coriander seeds. Leave over night. Strain and add 1/2 tsp Sugar and drink
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Take Ginger or Ginger tea
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat a lot of fresh fruits and vegetables, Eat celery/celery leaves
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat a low-salt diet
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid Sugary foods, Aged Meats, Nuts, Seeds, Cheese, Fried foods
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eliminate alcohol from the diet completely 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Quit smoking&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Insomnia</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Insomnia.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Insomnia</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
The term insomnia literally denotes a complete lack of sleep. It is, however, used to indicate a relative inability to sleep that consists of difficulty in falling asleep, difficulty in remaining asleep, early final awakening, or combinations of these complaints. This disease has assumed alarming proportions in the present times, especially among the upper classes in the urban set-up.  
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> -
The term insomnia literally denotes a complete lack of sleep. It is, however, used to indicate a relative inability to sleep that consists of difficulty in falling asleep, difficulty in remaining asleep, early final awakening, or combinations of these complaints. This disease has assumed alarming proportions in the present times, especially among the upper classes in the urban set-up.&lt;/p>

&lt;strong>Symptoms&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Difficulty falling asleep,  Sleeplessness
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Waking up often at night
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Difficulty returning to sleep after awakening in the middle of the night
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Waking too early 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Feeling that you haven’t slept at all, the next day, Drowsiness, Tiredness
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Racing mind; which causes people to keep shifting from being depressed to being over-excited and hyperactive
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Physical and Mental Fatigue
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Difficulty in concentrating, Lapses of memory, loss of coordination, Irritability
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Headaches and Migraines&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Causes of Insomnia&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Feelings like depression, anxiety and stress may affect a person’s ability to fall asleep
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Suppressed thoughts of resentment, anger, and bitterness
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Constipation, Overeating at night, going to bed hungry
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Too much intake of tea, caffeine or other stimulants
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Smoking
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Bladder ailments
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Hormonal imbalance
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Magnesium or iron deficiency
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Jet lag
&lt;/li>&lt;li>A side effect of some prescription medication (especially anti-depressant medication)&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Make your bedroom an inviting place. Keep the room free of clutter and distractions.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Be sure you have the right bed and mattress for your needs, dark curtains to block light, earplugs if night noises disturb you
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Use the bed only for sleeping
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Establish a regular sleep-wake cycle
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Reduce sleeping hours. Too much sleep can also cause insomnia.
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Curb the nap habit. Try to avoid naps during the day
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Limit your consumption of caffeine and other stimulants in the afternoon and evening
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Watch your alcohol intake
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Fit in some exercise during the day, but don't exercise strenuously right before bedtime
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat light meals in the evening&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Have a glass of warm milk or mango or  banana before going to bed
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Have Curd or Curd with Sugar or sweet Lassi before going to bed
&lt;/li>&lt;li>At night drink a spoon of Lemon juice mixed with a spoon of Honey
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Massage foot sole with Mustard oil before going to bed
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Rub a Cucumber piece on the foot sole  before going to bed it gives a cooling effect
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Soak &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poppy_seeds">Poppy seeds&lt;/a> in water for an hour, Grind to form a paste. Boil this paste with Milk and sugar and drink it
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Boil &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aniseed">Aniseeds&lt;/a> in water for 10 minutes, add Milk and Sugar and drink it before going to bed 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Grind Coriander leaves grinded with water and mix it with Sugar and eat this paste
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink a glass of Carrot juice everyday
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Consume Dry fruits and Oats regularly 
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat Indian gooseberry, Sprouted horse gram as they help cure insomnia&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Depression</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Depression.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Depression</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
Depression is one of the most common emotional disorders. It may be manifested in varying degrees: from feelings of slight sadness to utter misery and dejection. The growing complexities of modem life and its resultant crises, as well as the mental stress and strain of day-to-day life, usually leads to this disorder.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> - &lt;br/>
Depression is one of the most common emotional disorders. It may be manifested in varying degrees: from feelings of slight sadness to utter misery and dejection. The growing complexities of modem life and its resultant crises, as well as the mental stress and strain of day-to-day life, usually leads to this disorder.&lt;/p>

&lt;strong>Symptoms&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Acute sense of loss, Inexplicable sadness, Loss of energy and fatigue
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Feelings of helplessness and hopelessness
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Loss of interest in daily activities
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Strong feelings of Worthlessness or Guilt
&lt;/li>&lt;li>You engage in Escapist behavior such as substance Abuse, Compulsive Gambling, Reckless Driving or Dangerous Sports
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Significant weight loss or weight gain
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Agitation, irritability
&lt;/li>&lt;li>A disturbed sleep is a frequent occurrence
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Loss of appetite, Giddiness, Nausea, Constipation
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Aches and pains all over the body
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Lack of concentration and Indecisiveness
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Low body temperature, Low blood pressure, Hot flushes and Shivering
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Talking about killing or harming oneself&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Causes of Depression&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Prolonged periods of Anxiety and Tension can cause mental depression
&lt;/li>&lt;li>The excessive and indiscriminate use of drugs also leads to faulty assimilation of vitamins and minerals by the body and ultimately causes depression
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Loneliness, Lack of social support
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Recent stressful life experiences
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Marital or relationship problems
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Financial strain
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Early childhood trauma or abuse
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Unemployment or underemployment
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Health problems or chronic pain
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Alcohol or drug abuse
&lt;/li>&lt;li>A side effect of some prescription medication
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Family history of depression&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Cultivating supportive relationships
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Getting regular exercise and sleep
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat healthy (a diet rich in veggies, fruits, nuts, whole grains, and fish) to naturally boost your mood
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid Alcohol and Drugs
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Managing stress
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Get your rest
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Practicing relaxation techniques
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Work on a positive attitude, Make a conscious effort to stop negative thoughts
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Set realistic goals and responsibilities
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Have an attitude of gratitude
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Build your self-esteem
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Stay connected with friends and family&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Eat an Apple, It can be eaten with Milk and Honey
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink a decoction of Coriander seeds and Honey
&lt;/li>&lt;li>A pinch of finely powdered cardamom seeds could be taken mixed with green tea
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Mix 1/8 teaspoon of nutmeg powder with 1 tablespoon of freshly extracted Indian Gooseberry juice. Consume this mixture thrice a day
&lt;/li>&lt;li>About thirty grams of the herb lemon Balm should be placed in half a litre of cold water and permitted to stand for 12 hours. The infusion should then be strained and taken in small doses during the day
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat Cashewnut, root of Asparagus
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat food rich in vitamin B such as Wholegrain, Green Vegetables, Eggs and Fish
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink Buttermilk
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Avoid Coffee, Alcohol, Chocolate, Colas, White Flour Products, Chemical Additives, White Rice, Sweets and Strong Condiments
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Follow a healthy diet, Regular exercise
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Soak feet in a hot water tub with rosemary leaves, chlorine and some soap added to it. Do this for about 20 minutes and then rub your feet
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Watch comedy movies or comedy shows
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Always try to spend time with your friends, so that it will make you feel better
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Never stay alone when you are depressed, Talk to people you trust
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Volunteer, Help others&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>&lt;p></Content>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <title>Stress</title>
    <ImagePath>images/SelfCure/Stress.png</ImagePath>
    <Element>Stress</Element>
    <Description>Description:-
Stress is a situation where the individual feels some sort of mental or emotional pressure. Individuals are often unaware that they are under stress. Stress usually produces a physical and emotional response in your body. This is actually good for you as it works to stimulate your body into action. However, over time, this may prove to be harmful to the body as it will continuously be exposed to the stressful state which will eventually have an adverse effect on your health.
    
For detailed description switch to fullscreen mode.</Description>
    <Content>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Description&lt;/strong> -
Stress is a situation where the individual feels some sort of mental or emotional pressure. Individuals are often unaware that they are under stress. Stress usually produces a physical and emotional response in your body. This is actually good for you as it works to stimulate your body into action. However, over time, this may prove to be harmful to the body as it will continuously be exposed to the stressful state which will eventually have an adverse effect on your health.&lt;/p>

&lt;strong>Symptoms&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Headache, Chest pain, Muscle tension or pain
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Fatigue, Sleep problems
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Anxiety, Restlessness, Lack of motivation or focus
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Depression, Irritability, Anger, Emotional outbursts
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Increased heart rate, Sweating and generally, Shortness of breath, Increased state of alertness
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Unable to concentrate, Becoming easily confused, Feeling you can't cope
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Having memory problems
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Thinking about negative things all the time, Negative self-talk
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Having marked mood swing
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Finding it hard to make decisions
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Overeating or Under-eating
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Stomach upset
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drug or alcohol abuse, Tobacco use
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Social withdrawal&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Causes of Stress&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Financial Problems
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Fear, Envy, Uncertainty
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Workplace Stress
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Personal Relationships
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Health – Heart diseases, hypertension, problems with eye sight etc
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Responsibility increase
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Loud noises, Blinding light, Severe heat or cold, X-rays and other forms of radiation, Drugs, Chemicals, Various toxic substances&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>How to avoid&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Meditation, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yoga">Yoga&lt;/a>, Regular exercise
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat healthy food and chew well. Don't eat just because you are bored, unhappy, or angry
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink lot of water
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Don’t smoke and consume alcohol
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Find a hobby which has no deadlines, no pressures, and which can be picked up or left easily, takes the mind off stresses
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Don't over commit yourself
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Be responsible for your work. Do your best with every opportunity
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Communicate with friends, Keep yourself happy&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>

&lt;strong>Self Help&lt;/strong> -
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Slowly breath in and very slowly breathing out. If you do this a few times, and concentrate fully on breathing, you may find it quite relaxing
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Chew twelve leaves of basil two times in a day, morning and evening, for preventing stress
&lt;/li>&lt;li>A tea can be prepared by pouring a cup of boiling water over one teaspoon of dried out or fresh sage leaves. The water should be enclosed and infused for several minutes. It should then be strained and sweetened with honey, if preferred
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink a glass of warm Milk with Honey and Cinnamon
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Drink hot Water with a spoonful of honey in it
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Smell &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carom_seeds">Carom seeds&lt;/a>
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Eat yogurt, sprouts
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Take a hot water bath
&lt;/li>&lt;li>Caffeine in Coffee and a lot of Soft drinks, Salt, Sugar, Cigarettes, and Alcohol should be avoided&lt;/li>&lt;/ul></Content>
  </Item>
</SelfCure>